Guide to the Radical Women National Office (Seattle) Records
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
Radical Women National Office (Seattle) records
1976-1998
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
6291
6291-001
Radical Women
1.28 cubic feet 1 box
Records of the national office of Radical Women, a socialist, feminist worker's organization based in Seattle, Washington. The records were collected and maintained by Clara Fraser, the co-founder and officer of Radical Women and the Freedom Socialist Party.
Radical Women (RW) is a socialist feminist organization. RW sought to become the socialist wing of the feminist movement. The organization was founded in Seattle in 1967 when Freedom Socialist Party co-founder Clara Fraser and her close colleague, Gloria Martin, joined with young women from Students for a Democratic Society to build women's leadership in the left and anti-war movements. In 1973, RW formally affiliated with the Freedom Socialist Party, and the party gained a sister organization. Other founding members include Melba Windoffer and Susan Stern.
RW is active in intersectional feminist socialist organizing against racism, sexism, homophobia, fascism, and labor exploitation. Their political analysis sees women's political action as essential in creating social change and trains women to lead these campaigns. They have been especially active in pressuring other feminist organizations into better representing women of color and the LBGTQ+ community.
SERIES 1: ADMINISTRATIVE MEETINGS, FINANCES, AND CORRESPONDENCE, 1976-1996
SERIES 2: CONFERENCES AND CONVENTIONS, 1976-1998
SERIES 3: MASS WORK, COALITIONS, AND EVENTS, 1977-1998
SERIES 4: PUBLICATIONS, LITERATURE, AND MEDIA, 1979-1997
SERIES 5: LOCAL CHAPTERS, 1977-1996
Subseries A: Seattle, Washington Radical Women Chapter, 1977-1996
Subseries B: Grays Harbor, Washington Radical Women Chapter, 1982
Subseries C: Portland, Oregon Radical Women Chapter, 1982-1992
Subseries D: Los Angeles, California Radical Women Chapter, 1982-1994
Subseries E: San Francisco, California Radical Women Chapter, 1979-1990
Subseries F: Juneau, Alaska Radical Women Chapter, 1979-1982
Subseries G: Mankato, Minnesota Radical Women Chapter, 1992
Subseries H: Melbourne, Australia Radical Women Chapter, 1990
The Radical Women National Office records (1976-1998) documents the activities of the national office of the organization, based in Seattle, Washington. They were collected and maintained by Clara Fraser, the co-founder and officer of Radical Women and the Freedom Socialist Party. This collection documents the evolution and collective actions of nationally recognized socialist feminist leaders from 1976-1998. The perspectives from leaders of the national office provides context to how RW has worked and grown their organization via the aid and creation of local offices. The records are especially valuable for researchers seeking to understand how radical organizations and movements evolve and shift through decades of adversity and pushback from the mainstream media and an inhospitable political environment.
This collection provides access to communication among the local and national RW organizers as well as materials concerning mass work such as the protection of Roe vs. Wade, the Seattle City Light fight for affirmative action for tradeswomen electrical workers, the collaborative 1997 Feminist Brigade to Cuba, the landmark Freeway Hall Case, and drafts of RW literature such as the Radical Women Manifesto.
Materials include correspondence, articles, newspaper clippings, press release materials, fliers, event programs, edited drafts and speeches, itineraries, legal documents, conference/event planning, and official newsletters. The content of the materials concern the organization’s planned events, recruitment, and opening communication channels that are centered on social activism, intersectional feminism, and providing a platform for feminist speakers.
The collection is arranged into the following series which contain:
SERIES 1: ADMINISTRATIVE MEETINGS, FINANCES, AND CORRESPONDENCE, 1976-1996: RW’s National Executive Committee papers, including correspondence, records on public relations, membership, and finances.
SERIES 2: CONFERENCES AND CONVENTIONS, 1976-1998: Records documenting RW’s involvement, including statements and positions, press releases, and communication in international and regional conferences and conventions.
SERIES 3: MASS WORK, COALITIONS, AND EVENTS, 1977-1998: Materials concerning RW organized events and activism in civil rights and labor movements.
SERIES 4: PUBLICATIONS, LITERATURE, AND MEDIA, 1979-1997: Position statements, speeches, bulletins, newsletters, media coverage, and political literature related to RW.
SERIES 5: LOCAL CHAPTERS, 1977-1996: Correspondence, finances, and event materials concerning the growth and participation of local RW chapters. Despite being local chapters, they include correspondence with national leaders such as Clara Fraser and Betty Friedan. The records of the Seattle chapter especially overlaps with that of the National Office.
No restrictions on access.
Forms part of the Labor Archives of Washington.
Donated by Helen Gilbert, who was custodian of Clara Fraser's RW records.
Radical Women Seattle Office records
Clara Fraser papers
Megan Cornish papers
Heidi Durham papers
Freedom Socialist Party Seattle Branch records
Freedom Socialist Party National Office (Seattle) records
Feminism$zWashington (State); Women$zWashington (State)$xSocieties and clubs; Women and socialism$zWashington (State); Radicalism$zWashington (State); Women's rights$zUnited States; Socialism$zWashington (State); Socialism$xSocieties, etc.; Feminism$xSocieties, etc.; Women and socialism$xSocieties, etc.; Radicalism$xSocieties, etc; Newsletters; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor History; Women; Seattle; Washington (State)
- ADMINISTRATIVE MEETINGS, FINANCES, AND CORRESPONDENCE, 1976-1996; SERIES 1 (Box-folder 1/1-32)
  - Nominating Committee 1976, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Jaan Laaman International Women's Day Greeting to Freedom Socialist Party on Behalf of All Ohio Seven, 1977 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - FBI File on Radical Women, 1978 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Funding and Sales 1979 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - National Executive Committee Correspondence 1979 - Constance Scott (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Correspondence with Attached Schedule for Freedom Socialist Party Forum Series and Membership Drive Proposal, 1979 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Response to Myra T. Weiss Letter, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Membership Recruiting, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Seattle - Clara Fraser and Max Reigel Memos, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Membership Correspondence, 1979-1982 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Committee and Branch Reports, 1979-1983 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Clara Fraser and Betty Maloney Memos, 1980-1983 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Correspondence on Finances and Fundraising, 1980-1983 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Sharman Haley Legal Victory Memo, 1981 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Report to Freedom Socialist Party, 1987 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Conference Coordination and National Identity, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - National Executive Committee Meeting Materials - New York City 1989 (Box-folder 1/17)
  - Clara Fraser and Luma Nichol Correspondence, 1990 (Box-folder 1/18)
  - Constance Scott and Guerry Hoddersen - San Francisco Meeting Correspondence, 1990 (Box-folder 1/19)
  - Ann O'Connell [?] and Clara Fraser Correspondence - Photographing Activism, 1990 (Box-folder 1/20)
  - Internal Conflict - Nancy Reiko Kato and Adrienne Weller, 1990 (Box-folder 1/21)
  - Fund Drive, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 1/22)
  - Happy International Women's Day from Clara Fraser to Merle Woo, 1991 (Box-folder 1/23)
  - Correspondence About Finances, 1991 (Box-folder 1/24)
  - Nancy Reiko Kato - Internal Conflicts and Political Priorities, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 1/25)
  - Correspondence About 1991-92 Financial Reports, 1992 (Box-folder 1/26)
  - Fund Drive Donation Allocation, 1993 (Box-folder 1/27)
  - Correspondence Regarding Financial Reports and Fund Drive, 1994 (Box-folder 1/28)
  - Graphic Identity Program, 1995 (Box-folder 1/29)
  - Nancy Reiko Kato Schedules and Work Contact Information, 1995 (Box-folder 1/30)
  - Recruitment Campaign and Finances 1995 - Nancy Reiko Kato (Box-folder 1/31)
  - Correspondence With National Organizer Nancy Reiko Kato, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 1/32)
- CONFERENCES AND CONVENTIONS, 1976-1998; SERIES 2 (Box-folder 1/33-52)
  - Annual Conference 1976 - Laura Teague Draft Report "A New Era for Women Workers, Minority Women, and Lesbians." (Box-folder 1/33)
  - 10th Anniversary Conference - Port Ludlow 1978 (1 of 2), 1977-1978 (Box-folder 1/34)
  - 10th Anniversary Conference - Port Ludlow 1978 (2 of 2), 1977-1978 (Box-folder 1/34)
  - International Meeting of Women 1977 Paris - Sandy Nelson on The American Feminist Movement (Box-folder 1/35)
  - National Radical Women -Washington State Conference for Women - Constance Scott Analysis, 1977 (Box-folder 1/36)
  - Women's Studies National Conference 1981 Correspondence and Report - Constance Scott (Box-folder 1/37)
  - Proposal for Participation In Yellow Springs Socialist Feminist Conference - Chicago 1985 - Guerry Hoddersen Memo to Constance Scott (Box-folder 1/38)
  - Democratic Socialist of America Socialist Feminist Conference - Memo from Constance Scott, 1985 (Box-folder 1/39)
  - Conference 1990 - "The Third Wave of Feminism: A Candidly Revolutionary Approach" - Santa Monica, California (Box-folder 1/40)
  - Conference Public Relations 1990 (Box-folder 1/41)
  - Conference Finances 1990 (Box-folder 1/42)
  - Proposal for Participation In Yellow Springs Socialist Feminist Conference - Chicago 1985 - Guerry Hoddersen Memo to Constance Scott, 1990 (Box-folder 1/43)
  - 1990 National Organization for Women Convention In San Francisco (Box-folder 1/44)
  - University of Natal Invitation - Women and Gender In Southern Africa Conference 1991, 1990 (Box-folder 1/45)
  - First International Asian Lesbian Conference Outreach - Joanne Oligario, 1991 (Box-folder 1/46)
  - Marxist Scholars Conference 1991 - Temple University, Philadelphia (Box-folder 1/47)
  - 21st Century Party Convention - Washington, D.C., 1992 (Box-folder 1/48)
  - National Radical Women - Greetings to The World Conference - Nancy Reiko Kato and Yolanda Alaniz, 1994 (Box-folder 1/49)
  - Gabriela Invitation - Women's International Solidarity Affair In The Philippines Conference 1994 (Box-folder 1/50)
  - Greetings to The United Nations Fourth World Conference on Women and Non-governmental Organizations Forum 1995 (Box-folder 1/51)
  - Stephen Durham Taller Internacional (International Workshop) At The Cuban Communist Party "Socialism Towards The 21st Century" Havana Conference 1997, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 1/52)
- MASS WORK, COALITIONS, AND EVENTS, 1977-1998; SERIES 3 (Box-folder 1/53-81)
  - Events - Seattle 1977 (Box-folder 1/53)
  - Sexual Politics Column - Radical Women Support Palestinian Rights - The Daily of The University of Washington 1970s, 1977 (Box-folder 1/54)
  - Women's Rights At Crossroads - Public Forum, 1977 (Box-folder 1/55)
  - Events 1978 (Box-folder 1/56)
  - Greetings to The World Conference - Nancy Reiko Kato and Yolanda Alaniz, 1979 (Box-folder 1/57)
  - Abortion and Reproductive Rights, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 1/58)
  - Constance Scott - Mccarthyite-like Attacks on The Chico Feminist Women's Health Center, 1981 (Box-folder 1/59)
  - Campus Radical Women Events 1981-83 - University of Washington, 1981-1983 (Box-folder 1/60)
  - Events 1981-83, 1981-1983 (Box-folder 1/61)
  - Ad Hoc Coalition of Women Event 1982 (Box-folder 1/62)
  - International Women's Day 1982 (Box-folder 1/63)
  - Coalition Fight - Seattle Reproductive Rights Alliance and National Organization for Women Censors Women of Color, 1983 (Box-folder 1/64)
  - "National Radical Women Day" Work Party, 1983 (Box-folder 1/65)
  - Roe Versus Wade and "FBI Versus Women", 1984-1985 (Box-folder 1/66)
  - Constance Scott on Women's Rights, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 1/67)
  - Freedom Socialist Party - Freeway Hall Case Defense Committee, 1990 (Box-folder 1/68)
  - Campus Radical Women Activity on International Women's Day 1990 (Box-folder 1/69)
  - Petition for A Labor Party to National Organization for Women, 1990 (Box-folder 1/70)
  - Nellie Wong Lecture on Racism, Sexism, and War - The Daily of The University of Washington, 1991 (Box-folder 1/71)
  - International and East European Speaking Tour, 1991-1994 (Box-folder 1/72)
  - March to Fight The Right - National Organization for Women Correspondence, 1991-1996 (Box-folder 1/73)
  - Supreme Court Ruling In The Pennsylvania Abortion Case - Valencia Hall, 1992 (Box-folder 1/74)
  - Socialist Feminist Study Group In Vancouver, Canada, 1992 (Box-folder 1/75)
  - International Feminist Brigade Proposal Edits and Cuban Mission Planning, 1994-1996 (Box-folder 1/76)
  - International Feminist Brigade, Cuba 1997 (1 of 3), 1994-1997 (Box-folder 1/77)
  - International Feminist Brigade, Cuba 1997 (2 of 3), 1996-1997 (Box-folder 1/77)
  - International Feminist Brigade, Cuba 1997 (3 of 3), 1996-1998 (Box-folder 1/77)
  - Freedom Socialist Party - Defense of Affirmative Action on University of California Campuses, 1995 (Box-folder 1/78)
  - Demand to Unionize Prostitutes - Guerry Hoddersen to Clara Fraser, 1995 (Box-folder 1/79)
  - International Feminist Brigade to Cuba Proposal - Marian Larkin Correspondence With The Federación De Mujeres Cubanas, 1996 (Box-folder 1/80)
  - Atlanta, Georgia Abortion Clinic Bombings Statement - Anne Slater, 1997 (Box-folder 1/81)
- PUBLICATIONS, LITERATURE, AND MEDIA, 1979-1997; SERIES 4 (Box-folder 1/82-102)
  - Executive Committee Drafts and Manifesto - Monica Hill, Constance Scott, Marcia Cutler, and Sharman Haley, 1979 (Box-folder 1/82)
  - Publications - Newsletter and Bulletin, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 1/83)
  - Publications, 1980-1983 (Box-folder 1/84)
  - Constance Scott's Review of Betty Friedan "The Second Stage", 1981 (Box-folder 1/85)
  - Womanews Erarticle - Constance Scott, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 1/86)
  - Fireweed Magazine Issue on Feminist Theory, Practice, and Vision, 1983 (Box-folder 1/87)
  - Joanna Russ - Published and Upcoming Literature, 1983 (Box-folder 1/88)
  - Manifesto, 1983-1990 (Box-folder 1/89)
  - Article on Pornography for The Guardian, 1984 (Box-folder 1/90)
  - Bulletin of The Centro De Documentación Sobre La Mujer - Lima, Peru, 1986 (Box-folder 1/91)
  - Participation on The Oprah Winfrey Show, Chicago 1987 - Emily Woo Yamasaki and Karen Brodine, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 1/92)
  - Article Submission for Spanish Feminist Party Magazine, 1990 (Box-folder 1/93)
  - Sparkplugs of Labor - Heidi Durham and Megan Cornish, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 1/94)
  - National Radical Women Publications - Nancy Reiko Kato - Women of Color: Frontrunners for Freedom, 1990-1995 (Box-folder 1/95)
    - Northwest Nikkei Newspaper Article December 1995 on Nancy Reiko Kato - Sandee Taniguchi
  - Merle Woo - Is National Organization for Women The Right Group for Lesbians? - The Advocate, 1991 (Box-folder 1/96)
  - National Radical Women Publications - Women of Color: Frontrunners for Freedom, 1991 (Box-folder 1/97)
  - What Have We Got to Lose? - Mary Ann Curtis of Campus Radical Women, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 1/98)
  - Nancy Reiko Kato - Freedom Socialist Subscription Sale Story, 1992 (Box-folder 1/99)
  - Sojourner: The Women's Forum July 1995 Page 20-21 Shared By Debra O'GARA (Box-folder 1/100)
  - Creative Pieces and Articles By Women Including Toni Medinicino, Clara Fraser, and Michele Wallace, 1995 (Box-folder 1/101)
  - Listed In Emerge Magazine - March 1997 Correspondence (Box-folder 1/102)
- LOCAL CHAPTERS, 1977-1996; SERIES 5 (Box-folder 1/103-133)
  - Seattle, Washington Radical Women Chapter, 1977-1996; Subseries A (Box-folder 1/103-120)
    - 1977-78 Records, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 1/103)
    - Events 1978 - Bush Mama (Box-folder 1/104)
    - Memos Between Clara Fraser and Mary Reeves, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 1/105)
    - Events 1979 (Box-folder 1/106)
    - Fundraising 1979-80 (Box-folder 1/107)
    - Events 1979-80 - Women's Superiority, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 1/108)
    - In The Media, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 1/109)
    - Events 1980 (Box-folder 1/110)
    - Events 1981 (Box-folder 1/111)
    - Invitation from Washington Women Lawyers - Judicial Candidate Forum Night, 1981 (Box-folder 1/112)
    - Memo Between Clara Fraser and Betty Maloney - Clique Fight 1981 (Box-folder 1/113)
    - Seattle Radical Women Organizer Betty Maloney Correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box-folder 1/114)
    - Events 1982 - Women In The Trades Public Forum (Box-folder 1/115)
    - Finances 1982 - Feminist Mobilization Fund and Memos (Box-folder 1/116)
    - Seattle Radical Women 1983, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 1/117)
    - Gloria Martin Correspondence, 1990 (Box-folder 1/118)
    - Anne Slater to Nancy Kato - New South African Canadian Member, 1995 (Box-folder 1/119)
    - Events 1996 - Sandy Nelson Case, Same-sex Marriage, and Gay Pride (Box-folder 1/120)
  - Grays Harbor, Washington Radical Women Chapter, 1982; Subseries B (Box-folder 1/121)
    - The Daily World - "Peace Bishop" Sparks Reaction By Sandy Nelson - February 1982 (Box-folder 1/121)
  - Portland, Oregon Radical Women Chapter, 1982-1992; Subseries C (Box-folder 1/122-124)
    - Correspondence from Branch Organizer Adrienne Weller to National Organizer Constance Scott, 1982 (Box-folder 1/122)
    - Correspondence from Branch Organizer Adrienne Weller to Workers Vanguard, 1992 (Box-folder 1/123)
    - Events 1979 (Box-folder 1/124)
  - Los Angeles, California Radical Women Chapter, 1982-1994; Subseries D (Box-folder 1/125-126)
    - Correspondence from Branch Organizer Monica Hill to National Organizer Constance Scott, 1982 (Box-folder 1/125)
    - Correspondence from Mary Ann Curtis on New Branch Organizer Donna Ramirez and Finance Director Christine Browning, 1994 (Box-folder 1/126)
  - San Francisco, California Radical Women Chapter, 1979-1990; Subseries E (Box-folder 1/127-129)
    - San Francisco Committee for A Revolutionary Socialist Party Member Mike Delacour - People's Park 10th Anniversary, 1979 (Box-folder 1/127)
    - Women Writers Union Partnership - Events and Membership, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 1/128)
    - Membership 1990 (Box-folder 1/129)
  - Juneau, Alaska Radical Women Chapter, 1979-1982; Subseries F (Box-folder 1/130)
    - Letter to Sharman Haley Regarding Participation In Common Ground, 1979-1982 (Box-folder 1/130)
  - Mankato, Minnesota Radical Women Chapter, 1993; Subseries G (Box-folder 1/131)
    - Midwest Adventures, Outreach, and Prospects - Carolyn Kanyusik[?], 1993 (Box-folder 1/131)
  - Melbourne, Australia Radical Women Chapter, 1990; Subseries H (Box-folder 1/132-133)
    - Report on Garage Sale - Alison Thorne, 1990 (Box-folder 1/132)
    - Melbourne Radical Women Study Group- Woman Workers: Sparkplugs of Labor, 1990 (Box-folder 1/133)